<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ane oration made by Master Theodore de Beze, minister of the word of God, accompanyed with. xi. other ministers and. xx. deputies of the refourmed churches of the realme of Fraunce, in the presence of the king, ... Tuesday the ix. day of September, 1561, in the noonnery of Poyssy. Truely gathered and set forth in suct sort as it was spoken by the said de Beze. Whereunto is added a brief declaration exhibited by the said Beze, to the Quene the mother, the next morowe after the making of the said oration, touching certain poyntes conteyned in the same</title>
            <title>Harangue faicte par M. Théodore de Bèze. English.</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119256</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854463</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19885</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10008)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19885)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1195:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ane oration made by Master Theodore de Beze, minister of the word of God, accompanyed with. xi. other ministers and. xx. deputies of the refourmed churches of the realme of Fraunce, in the presence of the king, ... Tuesday the ix. day of September, 1561, in the noonnery of Poyssy. Truely gathered and set forth in suct sort as it was spoken by the said de Beze. Whereunto is added a brief declaration exhibited by the said Beze, to the Quene the mother, the next morowe after the making of the said oration, touching certain poyntes conteyned in the same</title>
                  <title>Harangue faicte par M. Théodore de Bèze. English.</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robet [sic] Lekprewik. Cum priuilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Bèze, Théodore de.  La harangue faicte par M. Théodore de Bèze, .. accompagné d'autres unze ministres, et de vingt députez des églises réformées du royaume de France, devant le roy, .. The brief declaration is a translation of: Sommaire déclaration de Théodore de Besze, sur certains poinctz par luy proposez en l'assemblée .. à Poissy, le 9 de septembre mil cinq cens soixante et un.</note>
                  <note>D7v is a separate title page, reading: A briefe writing, exhibited by Master Theodore de Beze, to the Quene Mother at Poissy, the x. day of September .."; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-e.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Edinburgh. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poissy, Colloquy of, 1561 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Charles IX, 1560-1574 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>France --  Religious history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Ane ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made by maſter Theodore de Beze Miniſter of the word of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with xi. other Miniſters and xx. deputies of the refourmed Churches of the Realme of Fraunce, in the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the King, the Quene mother, the king of Nauarre, the princes of Conde, and of La Roche Surion, monſieur de Guiſe, the Conſtable, and other great Princes &amp; Lordes of the Kinges coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, being there alſo preſente vj. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles xxxvj. Archbiſhoppes &amp; Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, beſides a great number of Abbots, Priours, Doctours of the Sorbone and other Scooles: Tueſday the ix. day of September, 1561. in the Noonnery of Poyſſy. Truely gathered and ſet forth in ſuch ſort as it was ſpoken by the ſaid de Beze.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto is added a brief declaration exhibited by the ſaid Beze, to the Quene the mother, the next morowe after the making of the ſaid Oration, touching certain poyntes conteyned in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="oration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>Ane Oration made by Maſter Theodore de Beze, Miniſter of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of God, accompanied with xi. other Miniſters and with xx. deputies of the refourmed Churche of Fraunce, in the preſence of the King, the Quene the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the king of Nauarre, the Princes of Conde, and of La Rocheſuryon, and ſundrie other Princes and Lordes of the Counſel.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IRE, foraſmuch as the ſucceſſe of all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes be they great or ſmal, doth depend vpon Gods aſſiſtence eſpeciallye when the matter in queſtion appertaineth to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and doth ſurmount the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of our vnderſtanding: we truſt your Maieſtie will neither thinke it ſtraunge nor amiſſe, if we begin with the callinge of his
<pb facs="tcp:19885:3"/> Name, makynge to hym oure prayer in ſuch ſort as foloweth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="prayer">
                              <p>LOrd God Father eternall and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, we confeſſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge before thy holie maieſtie, that we be poore, wretched and miſerable ſinners, conceiued and borne in ſinne, inclined and giuen to yll, and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to all that good is: we tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe continually thy holye commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whereby we do purchaſe to our ſelfe by thy iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Neuertheleſſe Lord, we are right ſorie that we haue offended thee, &amp; do condemne our ſelues and our ſinnes, with true repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, deſiring that thy grace may aide our rewfull miſery. And foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed the to ſhew this day ſo much fauour to thy poore &amp; vnprofitable ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as to geue them meane to declare freely in the preſence of the king, whome thou haſt eſtabliſhed to reigne ouer them, and of the moſt noble and worthy company of the worlde, ſuch matter as it hath liked thee to geue them knowledge of, touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thy holy trueth: it may alſo pleaſe thee, O Lord &amp; Father of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth, according to thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed
<pb facs="tcp:19885:3"/> goodnes and mercies, ſo to kindle our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinges, ſo to gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; guide our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, framinge them to yelde to true teaching, &amp; ſo to conduct our ſpeache, that after we ſhal haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued according to the meaſure that it ſhal like thee to impart to vs the ſecrets which thou haſt ſhewed to men for their ſaluacion: we maye with all trueth and ſinceritie, ſet furth bothe with harte and tongue, ſuch matter as may ſerue to the glory &amp; honour of thy holy name, to the proſperitie and aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cement in honour of our king, and of all them that belong vnto him, with the reſt, quietneſſe, and comfort of the whole ſtate of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſpecially of this Realme of Fraunce. And this, O Lord and father almightie, we do require in the Name &amp; for the ſake of Ieſus Chriſte thy ſonne our Sauiour, praying to thee in ſuch ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te as him ſelfe hath taught vs to praye, Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>(.) All the aboue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Theodore de Beze knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, al his companie being in like ſort vpon their knees, who after the prayers made, riſing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued
<pb facs="tcp:19885:4"/> his ſpeache, as foloweth. (.)</p>
                  <p>Sire, it is no ſinal felicitie to a faithfull ſeruaunt, bearing his harty affection to his maiſter, to ſe the face and perſon of his liege Lord, forſomuche as the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentyng <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it ſelfe to him, as the Maieſtie as it were of God viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it can not be but the Subiect muſt thereby be greatly ſtirred to call to remembraunce the duetie, obedience, and ſubiection whiche he is bounde to owe vnto him. For being ſuche by nature as we be, that that we do beholde with the corporal eye (foreſeing the eye be good, and that the thing loked vpon do aunſwer to that that is conceiued of it) is of muche more effecte, then that that is conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red onely with a ſimple and naked apprehenſion of the minde. And in caſe it come ſo to paſſe that the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19885:4"/> ſaid Subiect be not onely admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Princes ſight, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth ſo muche fauour, as the Prince wyll be content to haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> alſo a ſight of him, and moreouer wyll vouchſafe to geue eare vnto him, and finally like ſuche matter as ſhal by him be vttered: he muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> nedes thereof receiue a meruelous ioye, and ſinguler comfort and contentacion.</p>
                  <p>The fruite and comfort of the which four pointes, Sire, it hath pleaſed God, vſing therein his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete iudgementes, that ſome of your right humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſubiectes haue of long tyme laked, to their greate griefe and ſorowe: vntyll that at the length by his infinite mercy, harkening vnto our teares &amp; continual mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, he hath ſhewed vs ſuche grace, as this daye hath brought to vs the good fortune that hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
<pb facs="tcp:19885:5"/> we haue wiſhed, rather then loked for, which is to ſe your maieſtie: Sire, and that more is, to be ſene and harde of the ſame, and of ſuch a noble and worthye company, as harde were it in the worlde to finde the like.</p>
                  <p>So as if we had neuer before receiued any benefite at your hand neither hereafter ſhoulde euer bee partakers of any from you, all the time that we haue to liue, coulde not ſuffiſe to prayſe God for this his benefite, and to geue worthy thankes therfore to your maieſtie. But with this, when we conſider that this ſaide day doth not onely open a meane to vs, but calleth vs, and as a man may ſay, by the gentle, cortoyſe, &amp; gracious coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce and demeanour whiche wee ſee in you ſo well becoomyng your Maieſtie, driueth vs to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe altogether our dueties, to
<pb facs="tcp:19885:5"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the Name of our God, and to declare the obedience that we beare to you: we muſt nedes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that our vnderſtandinge is not hable once to conceiue the greatneſſe of ſuch a benefite, and our tongues muche leſſe hable to vtter that, that our affections and good willes geueth them in char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to ſet forth. In ſuch ſorte, Sire, that this fauour paſſing all the eloquence of man, we thinke it is a great deal better to confeſſe our weakneſſe with a ſhamefaſte ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then to diminiſhe the grace of the benefite by the lacke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient ſpeache, for the due ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of the ſame</p>
                  <p>Our chief deſire is Sire, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine moſt ſpeciallye the fourth &amp; principal point, that is to ſaye, that our ſeruice whiche we offer this day, may be agreable and liked to your Maieſtie, whiche grace we
<pb facs="tcp:19885:6"/> truſt to winne at your Maieſties handes, the rather yf thereby it come to paſſe (which God graunt it may) that this our comming hither, may bring with it an end, not ſo muche of oure owne thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and miſeries, the memory whereof is halfe extincte by the good happe of this daye: as of a number of troubles &amp; diſorders, (whiche hath ben alwayes to vs more greuous then death coulde haue ben) fallen vpon the Realme, with the ruyne and deſtruction of ſo great a number of your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes.</p>
                  <p>Manye and diuerſe occaſions be there, that hath hytherto kept vs from the enioyinge of ſo great a grace, whereof we ſhould yet be in diſpaire, were it not that one the other ſide, many other thinges do maintaine our good hope, and put vs in ſome aſſuraunce. Firſt
<pb facs="tcp:19885:6"/> there is by the malice and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the tyme, an aſſured perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion rooted in manye mens hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that we be vnquiet, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ambitious men, geuen to our fantaſies, and enemies of al concorde and tranquilitie.</p>
                  <p>Others there be perhaps, who ſuppoſe that albeit it may be that we be not altogether enemies of concord, yet that we do demaund it, and bee content to come to it, with ſo ſharpe and heard condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, as were not conuenient we ſhould with them be receyued, as though we prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to ouerturne the preſent ſtate of the world, and to make a new of our owne faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyng, and to ſpoyle a number of their goods and riches, to enriche our ſelues withall.</p>
                  <p>There are beſides theſe, Sire, ſundry other lyke, or rather grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lettes, but we deſire rather,
<pb facs="tcp:19885:7"/> that the memorie of them may be buried, then to renewe by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall of them, olde ſores, being now come not to complaine, or to open griefes, but to ſeke out the moſt conuenient &amp; ſpedie remedye for them. And who then geueth vs ſuch an aſſuraunce in the middes of ſo many lettes and hinderaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? It is not, Sire, the leaning to any thinge that is in oure ſelues, who be in all reſpectes the baſeſt, and moſt vile in eſtimacion, of any ſort of men. Neither is it (GOD therefore bee thanked) vaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, or arrogauncie, for oure poore &amp; low eſtate beareth it not. It is, Sire, rather our vpryght conſcience, which aſſureth vs that our cauſe is good and iuſt, of the which we truſt God wil be prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour and defendour. It is alſo the natural goodnes whiche we doe note in your face, ſpeache, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.
<pb facs="tcp:19885:7"/> It is the equitie which<note place="margin">To the Quene mother.</note> we ſee and learne by experience to be grauen in your heart Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. It is the righteouſnes, and<note place="margin">To the King of Nauar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> vpryghtneſſe in iudgement, which we finde in you, Sire, and in the reſt of thee blood royall. And a great and manifeſt occaſion haue we to hope well in that our truſt is, that you my right honorable lordes of the Counſayle, reducing<note place="margin">The co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e.</note> yourſelfe all to one conformitie of good meaninge, will haue no leſſe good will and affection, to graunt vnto vs ſo holy and neceſſarie an agreement, as we haue to recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it. And what more? There is yet one thinge that enterteineth vs in right good confidence. And that is, that we do preſume ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of charitie, that you my lordes the Prelates, with<note place="margin">Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> whome we haue to conferre, will rather do your beſt with vs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:19885:8"/> to oure little meaſure, to ſet forth and bring to light the trueth, then to darken it, to teach rather then to contende, to waye our reaſons rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to trauaill to argue againſt them. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye rather to ſtaye that the diſeaſe go no further, then to make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable and deadly. This is the<note place="margin">Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> opinion we haue conceiued of you my Lordes, beſeching you in the Name of that great God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath brought vs here together, and that ſhalbe iudge bothe of our though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſayinges, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whatſoeuer hathe bene ſpoken, written, or done, in the ſpace of theſe xl. yeares paſte, or there about, you will ſpoile your ſelues, (like as for oure parte we minde to do the ſame) of all ſuche paſſions and preiudices, as maye hinder the good fruite, that is to be truſted ſhall ſuccede of ſo holy
<pb facs="tcp:19885:8"/> and commandable an enterpriſe: and that it may pleaſe you to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your ſelfes (in the whiche opinion God willing you ſhal not be deceiued) that you ſhall fynde in vs a ſprite tractable and ready to receiue whatſoeuer ſhalbe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the pure worde of God.</p>
                  <p>Thinke not that we be come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to maintaine anye errour but to diſcloſe and to amende what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer may be founde out of the waye, eyther on your ſyde, or on ours. Eſteme vs not ſo outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſlye preſumptuous, that we wolde once pretend to ouerthrow that we knowe to be eternall, to witt, the Churche of God: Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do you beleue that we go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and ſeke meanes to mak you like vnto vs, in our poore and vile effate, wherewith neuertheleſſe, thankes be geuen to God, we find our ſelues very well contented.
<pb facs="tcp:19885:9"/> Our deſire is to haue the ruynes of Ieruſalem repaired, the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall temple to be ſet vp agayne, the houſe of God whiche is builte with liuing ſtones to be ſette a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in his entier eſtate, and that the flockes ſo ſcattered and ſtrayed by the iuſt vengeaunce of God and negligence of man, may be knitte together againe, and brought in one companye to the ſhepefolde of him that is the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne and onely ſhepheard.</p>
                  <p>This is the mark we ſhoote at: This is our whole meanyng, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire &amp; intent (my Lordes) whiche in caſe heretofore you haue hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleued, our truſte is that you will be eaſely brought to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of it, when we ſhall haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to you by conference, ſuche matter as hath pleaſed God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due vs with, in all modeſtie and pacience. And woulde God that
<pb facs="tcp:19885:9"/> without any further trauaylling we mought in the ſtede of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one againſt the other, all with one voyce ſynge a ſonge vnto the Lord, and offer oure handes the one ſyde to the other, as it hath chaunſed at ſome tymes paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene two armyes of Pagans &amp; Infidelles ſet in battaile array. A foule ſhame muſt it nedes be to vs, that profeſſinge the ſtate of preachers of the doctrine of peace and concorde, we be ſo eaſely ſet a ſunder, and ſo harde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and vneaſy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to be tyed againe together in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne vnitie. But what ſhall we ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Men maye, and ought to wyſhe that all thinges were well, but it is God alone that muſt graunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, whiche he wyll do when it ſhall pleaſe him, to couer oure ſinnes with his goodneſſe; and chaſe awaye oure darkeneſſe with his lyght.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:10"/>
                  <p>And hauing thus muche ſaid, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, to the intent it may be knowen that our meaning is to proceade with good and vpright conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſimply, plainly, and roundly, we meane if your Maieſtie geue vs leaue ſo to do, to declare in a ſhort fourme the principal points of this conference, in ſuch ſort as God willing no man ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to be therwith offended.</p>
                  <p>There are ſome men that do think, and wold gladly perſwade all others to thinke the like, that our diſagreing doth ſtande in no greate matters of importaunce, but conſiſteth rather in thinges indifferent, then in the ſubſtancial pointes of our faith.</p>
                  <p>Others there be all of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that for lacke of good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of our beliefe, take it as though we agreed in nothing, no more then Iewes or Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metiſtes.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:10"/>
                  <p>The opinion of the firſt ſort is not ſo much to be diſcommended, as the iudgement of the laſt ſort is vtterly to be reiected: Like as we truſt ſhall appeare by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of our matter.</p>
                  <p>But ſurely, neither of them both do make any waye or ouertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of any true or aſſured concord. For if the laſte be beleued, none of the parties can purchaſſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſure ſtanding, but with the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwinge of the other, whiche were to cruell to think, and moſt horrible to be executed. If the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the firſt ſhould be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it muſte nedes be that many thinges ſhould remaine vndecided whereof ſhoulde riſe a very daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and hurtfull diſagreing.</p>
                  <p>To enter then into the matter, we do confeſſe (in the whiche ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we haue much a do to contain
<pb facs="tcp:19885:11"/> our teares: we confeſſe I ſay, that as we do agree in ſome principal pointes of the Chriſtian faith, ſo do we diſagree in ſome vthers.</p>
                  <p>We confeſſe one onely God, in one &amp; ſelfe ſame eſſence, infinitie, and incomprehenſible, diſtincte in three perſons conſubſtancials, and in all pointes coequall. That is to ſay: the Father vnbegotten, the ſonne from euer begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Father, and the holy Goſt procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge from the Father and the Sonne.</p>
                  <p>We confeſſe one onely Ieſus Chriſte, very God and very man, without confuſion or ſeparation of the two natures, or of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>We confeſſe that touching his manhood, he is not the ſonne of Ioſeph, but was conceiued by the ſecrete power of the holie Goſte in the wombe of the bleſſed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb facs="tcp:19885:11"/> Marie, virgin we ſay bothe before her deliueraunce and after alſo.</p>
                  <p>We confeſſe his Natiuitie, his lyfe, his death, his burying, his going downe into hell, his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and his aſcention, as they be contained in the holy Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>We beleue that he is on hyghe in heauen, ſett at the right hand of the Father, from whens he wil not departe till he come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
                  <p>We beleue in the holie Goſt, who lightneth vs, comforteth vs and ſupporteth vs.</p>
                  <p>We do beleue that there is one holie Catholike, that is to ſaye, vniuerſall Churche, which is the companie and congregation of Saintes, out of the which ther is no ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>We do aſſure our ſelues of the free remiſſion of our ſinnes, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:19885:12"/> the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, by the vertue wherof, after the ſame body of ours beinge rayſed from death to life ſhalbe ioyned againe with oure ſoules, we ſhall enioye with God the bleſſed and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. How then will ſome ſaye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are not theſe the articles of our faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein then ſtandeth the difference betwene vs?</p>
                  <p>Firſt, we differ in the expoſition of ſome part of them. Secondly, in that it ſemeth to vs (wherein if we be deceiued we wolde be glad to knowe it) that men haue not ſatiſfied them ſelues with theſe articles: but of longe tyme haue not ceaſed to adde article vpon article, as though Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion were a building that neuer would haue ende.</p>
                  <p>We ſay moreouer that ſuch buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding as hath bene made of newe, hath not as farre as we can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb facs="tcp:19885:12"/> ben alway builded vpon the olde foundacion: and therfore hath it rather taken awaye the grace of the olde buildinge, then ſerued to the garniſhing and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of the ſame. And yet haue men cleaued more to thoſe acceſſaries, then they haue done to the principall.</p>
                  <p>This is the ſumme ſhortlye of that we beleue and teache: but to the ende that our meaninges may be the better conceiued, we will diſcourſe the pointes more perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly.</p>
                  <p>We ſay then, and truſte to maintaine the ſame with all the temperaunce we can, by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonye of holye Scriptures, that the verie God in whom we ought to beleue, is ſpoyled of his perfecte Iuſtice, yf menne thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to ſette againſte his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and iuſte iudgemente<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any
<pb facs="tcp:19885:13"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> kinde of purgation or ſatiſfaction in this worlde, or in the other, then that whole entier and perfect obedience, which can not be founde in anie other, but only in Ieſus Chriſt. And in like ſort yf we ſaye, that he acquiteth vs of one part of our debtes, ſo as we pay the other, we ſpoyle him of his perfite mercy.</p>
                  <p>Hereof riſeth it as farre as we can iudge, that beinge the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, by what title we looke to be placed in heauen, we muſte holly and onely ſticke to the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt oure Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and redemer, or els ſhal we be driuen to worſhip a ſtraunge God, which ſhould not be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly either iuſt, or mercifull.</p>
                  <p>And hereof alſo dependeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point, of no ſmall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, touching the office of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. For if he be not onely
<pb facs="tcp:19885:13"/> and entierly oure ſaluation, this precious Name of Ieſus, that is to ſay Sauiour, denounced by the Angell Gabriell, ſhould not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly appertaine to him: likewiſe yf he be not our onely Prophete, hauinge fully declared the will of God his Father for our ſaluation: firſt by the mouth of his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and after that, when the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the tyme was come in his owne perſon, and finally by his faithfull Apoſtles. If he bee not alſo the head and ſpirituall kinge of oure conſciences, yf he be not our onely Prieſt for euer, after the order of Melchiſedech, hauing by one oblation once made of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe whiche neuer can be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, reconciled man with God, and is nowe in heauen, our onely interceſſour, till the ende of the worlde. To make an ende if we be not holie complete in hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
<pb facs="tcp:19885:14"/> the Name and title of Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, or Chriſte, that is to ſay an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and dedicated of God the Father to that effect, can not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto him.</p>
                  <p>If then we can not content our ſelues with his onely word faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached, and afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred and truely recorded by writinge by his Prophetes and Apoſtles, it is as muche as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe him of the degree of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete. And in caſe alſo we wil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke new lawes, to binde the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men, we take from him the dignitie of the head and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual kingdome of the Church. And whoſoeuer ſhal take vpon him, to offer him for the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes or ſhal not be content to take him for our onely interceſſour and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate in heauen, betwene God &amp; man, he taketh from him the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of his euerlaſting prieſthod.
<pb facs="tcp:19885:14"/> Thirdly we diſagree in the defini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſpring &amp; the effects of faith, which we tearme with S. Paul, iuſtifying faith, by the which only we do affirme that Ieſus Chriſt &amp; all his merites be applied to vs.</p>
                  <p>Touching good workes, if any man thinke that we ſet not by them, he is muche miſenfourmed, for we do no more ſeparate faith from charitie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heate and light can bee ſaperated from the fyre. And we ſay with S. Iohn in his firſt Canonicall Epiſtell, that he that ſaieth he knoweth God, and kepeth not his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundamentes, lieth, and no trueth is in him.</p>
                  <p>But concerning this purpoſe, we confeſſe plainly that we diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in thre principall pointes.</p>
                  <p>The firſt, touching the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; the ſpring from the which good workes do procede.</p>
                  <p>The ſeconde, what workes bee
<pb facs="tcp:19885:15"/> good workes.</p>
                  <p>The third, to what reſpect they bee good.</p>
                  <p>Touchinge the firſt, we finde none other free will in man, but that whiche receiueth freedome by the only grace of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte. And we ſay, that our nature being in the ſtate whiche it is fallen into, nedeth before all other thinges not to be aided and vpholden, but to be mortified and killed by the vertue of the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of God, for ſo muche as his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce findeth it not onely wounded &amp; much weakned, but altogether deſtitute of force and repugning to al good, yea dead &amp; rotten in ſinne and corruption. And therefore do we not to him ſo much diſhonour as to make oure ſelues parteners with him, to whoſe grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie working in vs, is to be geuen the beginninge, the myddle, and
<pb facs="tcp:19885:15"/> the ende of our good workes.</p>
                  <p>Touching the ſecond point, we do not receiue anye other rule of iuſtice and obedience before God, but his commaundementes as they be written and regiſtred in his holy worde, to the which we do not take it lawefull for anye man to adde or diminiſh, to binde therwith mans conſcience.</p>
                  <p>Touchinge the thirde point to witte in what reſpect they bee good: our beliefe is, that ſo farre foorth as they procede from the Spirite of God working in vs, they ought to be called good, for that they iſſue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo good a ſpring, and yet yf God ſhoulde examine them rigorouſly, there wolde be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounde matter inough and inough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the diſaduauntage of them.</p>
                  <p>We ſaye further, that they be good in another reſpecte, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſaye: forſomuche as God is by
<pb facs="tcp:19885:16"/> them glorified, men bee drawen to the knowledge of him, and we all bee aſſured the Spirite of God being in vs, which is knowen by his effectes, that we bee of the number of the elected, and of them that be predeſtinated to ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>But if a queſtion be moued, by what title euerlaſtinge life doth appertaine vnto vs, we ſay with S. Paule, that it is a free gyft of God, and no recompence any way due vnto oure merites. For Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in this behalfe inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth vs by his onely iuſtice, being imparted to vs, ſanctifieth vs by his onely holynes, beinge by him freely geuen to vs, and hath redemed vs by his onely Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which is auailable to vs, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in vs a true and a liuely faith by the grace onely and liberalitie of God.</p>
                  <p>All thoſe treaſures be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated
<pb facs="tcp:19885:16"/> to vs by the power of the holie Goſt, vſinge for that effect the preachinge of the Goſpell of God, and the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his holy Sacramentes. Not for that he nedeth any ſuch matter for the putting in vre of his ſaid power, he being almightie: but for that it pleaſeth him to be ſerued with theſe ordinary meanes, to breede and nouriſhe in vs the precious gift of faith, whiche is as it were the onely hand, and the onely veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to take holde of Ieſus Chriſt, and to receiue him with all his treaſures to our ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>And to the intent we maye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what we doe admitte for the worde of GOD: we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte nothinge but the doctrine written in the holie Prophetes, and the Apoſtles, tearmed the newe and olde Teſtament. For by whom ſhall we aſſure vs of oure
<pb facs="tcp:19885:17"/> ſaluation; but by ſuche a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> thereof, without reprothe, &amp; againſt whom none exceptions can be taken.</p>
                  <p>And touching the writinges of auncient doctours and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles, we thinke it conuenient before we do receiue them, as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereunto nothing can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne ſayde, to conferre them throughly, and to ſee them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the holy Scriptures &amp; amonges them ſelues alſo, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the Spirite of God is neuer diſagreing from it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Whiche we beleue (my Lords) you wil neuer go about to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe: yf you do, yt ſhall lyke you to pardon vs yf we do not beleue till we do ſee it doone, that you ſhall euer be hable to bringe it to paſſe.</p>
                  <p>Howe then? are we of the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed race of Cam, the ſonne of Noe
<pb facs="tcp:19885:17"/> who diſconered the pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> of his Father? Do we thinke oure ſelues more conning and better learned then ſo many auncient doctours bothe Greekes and Latiues? Be we ſo preſumptuous, as to thinke that we are the firſt that brought trueth to light, and to condemne the whole worlde of ignoraunce? God forbyd (my Lordes) that we ſhould be ſuche: but it maye like you to remember that there hathe ben Councels and Councels, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and doctours, for theſe he not the firſte dayes that falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes haue ben in the Churche of God, of whom the Apoſtles haue geuen vs warning in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, namely in the fourth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the firſte to Timothye, and Act. the xx. Secondly, touchinge the ſayde auncient writtinges, foraſmuche as all trueth that may be founde in them muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:19885:18"/> by drawen out of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: what more ſure waye can we finde to ſtudie, and vſe them to oure profite, then to trye them by that touche ſtone, and to waye and conſider the teſtimonies and reaſons of the Scriptures, vpon the whiche they haue grounded their expoſitions.</p>
                  <p>Surely no man can or ought to attribute anye more to them, then their ſelues do require: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon harken what S. Iherome ſaith vpon the Epiſtle to the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians. The doctrine (ſaith he) of the holy Goſte, is that which is ſet foorth in the Scripture and Canonicall writtinges, againſte the whiche if Councelles ſhall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deine any thinge, it is vnlawfull, and not to be admitted. And S. Auguſtine writtinge to Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian: We ought not (ſaith he) to accompte the reaſons and diſpn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions
<pb facs="tcp:19885:18"/> of men, of what eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and howe Catholike ſoeuer they be, or haue bene, in equal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or of ſuche an aucthoritie, as it maye not be lawfull for vs, (the reuerence due to ſuche perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages reſerued) to reproue and reiecte any thinge in their wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, wharein it may be founde that they haue iudged other wiſe then trueth will beare them being ſo founde and vnderſtode, with the helpe of Gods grace, by me or by any others. This thinke I of other mens wrytinges, and the ſame libertie do I geue to ſuch as ſhall take the paines to be readers of any thinge that my ſelfe ſhall write. As muche to the ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce writeth he in his 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Epiſtle, and in lyke ſorte in his ſeconde booke 37. Chapiter againſt Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſconius.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:19"/>
                  <p>Saint Ciprian alſo writteth in the ſame wiſe, ſaying that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth vs not to regarde what this man or that man hath done before our times: but what Ieſus Chriſt hath done before all mens tymes. And the ſame rule geueth S. Auguſtine, writting to Saint Iherome. And in another place diſputing againſt them, that for the maintenaunce of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions alleaged the autoritie of the Councell of Arimine: Lette vs grounde our ſelfe (ſaith he) ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I vpon the Councel of Nice, whiche neuertheleſſe is the moſte auncient approued Councell: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you vpon the Councel of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, but lette vs cleaue and ſtand faſt to the holy Scriptures. Saint Chriſoſtome was of the ſame opinion, who in his ſeconde expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon Saint Matthew in his xlix. Homely, ſayth: The
<pb facs="tcp:19885:19"/> Churche ſtayeth it ſelfe vpon the foundacion of the Prophetes and the Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>And to conclude in this matter, we do receiue and take the holie Scriptures for an entier and a perfect declaration of all thinges neceſſary for oure ſaluation. And touching ſuche matter as may be found in Councels, or the bookes of any auncient doctours, we can not nor ought not to let you, but that you maye alleage them to your ayde, and we alſo, ſo as it be grounded vpon the expreſſe tiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the holy Scripture. But for the loue of God, bring not to vs their bare authoritis, vnleſſe the ſame be throughly examined vpon the touch ſtone before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned. For we ſaye with Saint Auguſtine, in his ſeconde booke of Chriſtian doctrine, in the vi. Chapter: If there fall any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie
<pb facs="tcp:19885:20"/> in the interpretation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye one paſſage, the holye Goſte hath ſo tempered the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as that whiche is in one pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce obſcuredly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is in an other place ſpoken more clerely.</p>
                  <p>And thus much for this pointe, which I haue drawen ſome what the more at length, to the intente that all men may vnderſtand that we be not enemies to councelles, neither to the holy fathers, by the whiche it hath pleaſed God to tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che and inſtruct his Church.</p>
                  <p>There are yet two matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde, to witte, the matter of the Sacramentes, and the diſcipline and pollicie of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Touching the firſte: trueth it is that it were requiſite, it were treated of at good length, becauſe of the difficulties that be this day thereof in the ſtate of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But becauſe I haue not
<pb facs="tcp:19885:20"/> at this tyme taken vpon me to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, but rather to ſette foorth ſhortely the principall poyntes of oure conference: I will contente my ſelfe to declare ſummarelie what we do thynke, and holde therein.</p>
                  <p>We be as I take it concerning this word Sacrament, of one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, to witte: that Sacraments be ſignes viſible, by meanes whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof the coniunction and vnitie whiche we haue with oure Lord Ieſus Chriſt, is not to vs ſimplie ſignified or figured, but is to vs verelye and truely offered on the behalfe of the Lord, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ratified, ſealed, and as it were grauen by the vertue of the holie Goſt, in ſuche as by true faith do apprehend, and take hold of that whiche is to them ſo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and preſented.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:21"/>
                  <p>I vſe this worde ſignified (my Lordes) not meaninge thereby to weake or to diminiſhe the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Sacramentes, but to note a difference betwene the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne, and the thinge that ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it in all vertue and efficacie.</p>
                  <p>We do alſo agree that to the Sacramentes, there is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie required a celeſtiall and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall mutation. For we do not ſay that the water of the holy Baptiſme, is ſimplie water, but that it is a true Sacrament of oure regeneration, and of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of oure ſoules, by the blood of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
                  <p>In like ſort we do not ſay, that in the holy Supper of the Lord, the brrad is ſimplie bread: but that it is the Sacrament of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious body of oure Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which was deliuered for vs. Neither that wine, is only and
<pb facs="tcp:19885:21"/> ſimplie wine: but that it is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament of the precious blood which was ſhed for vs.</p>
                  <p>But here with we do not ſay, that this mutation is made in the ſubſtaunce of the ſignes, but in the vſe and end for the which they be ordeined. Neither do we ſaye that they bee made by vertue of certaine wordes pronounced, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the entent of him that pronounceth the ſame: but by the onely power and will of him that ordeined this heauenly and godly action, whoſe ordinaunce in this behalfe, ought to bee rehearſed with a loude voyce, and in ſuche language, as the aſſiſtauntes do vnderſtand, to whom it ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to bee plainely expounded, to the intent they may vnderſtande it, and receiue it accordingly: And thus muche concerninge the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb facs="tcp:19885:22"/> ſignes. Let vs nowe come to that, that is teſtified and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited of the Lord by theſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes.</p>
                  <p>We do not ſay, as ſome for lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of good vnderſtanding of vs, do iudge, that we do teache, that is to ſay, that in the holie Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord, there is nothing but a ſimple and naked remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the death of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Neither do we ſay, that by the ſayde holye Supper, we be made partakers onely of the fruite of his death and paſſion, but we do ioyne the grounde with the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that come of it, ſaying with Saint Paule in his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians, the tenth Chapiter: That the bread whiche we breake in ſuche ſort as he hath ordeined, is the communication
<pb facs="tcp:19885:22"/> of the very body of Ieſus Chriſt, that was deliuered for vs. And the Cuppe whereof we drinke, is the Communication of the verye blood that was ſhedde for vs, yea in the ſame ſubſtaunce that he to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in the womb of the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and that he caried from vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen.</p>
                  <p>And I pray you (my Lordes) in the Name of God, what canne you ſeeke or finde in this holye Sacrament, but we do ſeeke and ſinde the ſame alſo.</p>
                  <p>I do vnderſtand what you wil ſay ſtraight. Some of you wil require vs, to confeſſe that the bread and wine be tranſfourmed: I ſaye not into the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the bodie and blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, for that haue we confeſſed all readie, but into the very naturall body, &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:19885:23"/> and naturall blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Others peraduenture will not preſſe vs ſo narowly, but will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire vs to agree, that the bodie and blood be reallye and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally other within, or with, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bread.</p>
                  <p>In whiche point (my Lordes) I beſeche you for the honour of God, to geue eare to vs paciently, without takinge anye offence of oure ſayinges, and for a tyme to put away all the yll opinion that you haue conceiued of vs.</p>
                  <p>When either the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe two opinions ſhalbe by the holy Scripture proued to vs, we yelde oure ſelues readie to embrace it, and to ſtande to it to the death. But for the ſmall meaſure of knowledge, that it hath pleaſed God to impart vnto vs, it ſemeth that this tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, agreeth not in any
<pb facs="tcp:19885:23"/> ſimilitud and conuenien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie of our faith, faraſmuche as it is directly contrary to the true nature of the Sacramentes. In the whiche it is neceſſary that the ſubſtanciall Sygnes contymie, being true Signes of the ſubſtaunce of the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſte. And beſides this, it ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the veritie of mans nature in Chriſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of his aſcention. The ſame do I ſaye of the ſeconde opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that is of the conſubſtancia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whiche hath no foundation vpon the worde of Ieſus Chriſt, and is neuer a whit neceſſarie to make vs partakers of the fruite of the Sacramentes.</p>
                  <p>If heerupon anye man will<note place="margin">This place he ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d leth againe in his declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> aſke vs, whether our mindes bee to ſeelude Ieſus Chriſt from his Supper, we ſay we meane no ſuch mater. But if we haue regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to the diſtaunce of places, as
<pb facs="tcp:19885:24"/> muſte nedes haue, when the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion riſeth of the corporall preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and of his humanitie, diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, we ſaye his bodie is ſo farre from the bread and wine, as the greateſt heigth of heauen, is diſtaunte from the earth, forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as touching vs, we bee vpon the earth and ſo be the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes alſo, and touching him his fleſhe is in heauen, in ſuch ſort glorified, that as Saint Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſayeth, hath not taken away the nature of a verye bodye, but hath rydde from it all infirmities and imperfections belonging na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turallie thereunto.</p>
                  <p>And if anye body will hereof conclude, that hereby we make Ieſus Chriſt to be away from his holy Supper, we anſwere that he concludeth a wrye, for we doe to God this honour, that we beleue according to his word, that albeit
<pb facs="tcp:19885:24"/> his body preſently is in heauen, and in none other place, and we vpon the earth, and not elles where, we bee neuertheles made partakers of his bodie and blood, in a ſpirituall ſort, by meane of faith, as verely as we ſe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes with oure eyes, touch them with oure handes, put them in our mouthes, and liue with the ſubſtaunce of them, in this corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life.</p>
                  <p>You ſee in a ſumme (my Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) what our beliefe is in this point, which as ſemeth to vs (and in caſe we be deceiued we woulde be glad to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it) offered no violence to the wordes of Ieſus Chriſt, neither yet to the article of Aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, neither to the ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation of the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, neither yet openeth away to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, curious and comberſome to be diſſolued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:25"/>
                  <p>And further it hindreth not our coniunction and vnitie with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, for the whiche ende principally the ſayde Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were ordeined, and not to be worſhipped, ſhewed, kept, or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about, neither yet offered to God. And to make an ende: This beliefe, if we be not deceiued, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth more honor to the power and worde of the Sonne of God, then doth the other that ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the body of Chriſt to be really coupled with the ſignes, or els we mought not be partakers thereof.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not nede to touche any point of that may concerne the adminiſtration of Baptiſme, for that I am ſure none of you (my Lordes) will thinke ſo ill of vs, as to accoumpte vs to be of the ranke of the Anabaptiſtes, which ſect hath this day no greater ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies then we be to it. And as for
<pb facs="tcp:19885:25"/> other particuler queſtions in this matter, we truſt with the ayde of God, that being the principal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie agreed vpon, by this frendly and quiet conference, the reſt will take end of it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Touching other commonlie called holy Sacramentes: trueth it is that we can not gene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that name, tyll we be better taught ſo to do by holy Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>And yet in the meane tyme we<note place="margin">Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> thinke we haue ſufficiently aſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſihed the true confirmation, the office whereof is to catechiſe, and to inſtruct ſuche as haue bene baptized in their infancie, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all perſons before they ought to be admitted to the holy Supper.</p>
                  <p>We teache alſo true penitence,<note place="margin">Penaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce.</note> whiche lyeth in the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of oure fautes, and the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the parties by vs offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:19885:26"/> either publikelie or perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerlye, and in the abſolution whiche we haue by the blood of Chriſte, and in the amendinge of our liues.</p>
                  <p>We do allowe Matrimonie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording<note place="margin">Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.</note> to the ordinaunce of S. Paule, in all them that haue not the gyfte of continencie, to the whiche, we think not to be lawful to binde any perſon, by vowe, or perpetuall profeſſion, and with that we condemne all whordome, wantouneſſe, and looſenes, both in wordes, geſture, and dedes.</p>
                  <p>We do very wel admit degrees in Eccleſiaſticall charges, in ſuche<note place="margin">Orders</note> ſort as God hath ordained them in his houſe by his holy worde.</p>
                  <p>We do alſo allowe viſitations of the ſicke, as a principall part of the holy miniſtery of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>We do teache with S. Paule no man to be iudged in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb facs="tcp:19885:26"/> of dayes and meates, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that the kingdome of God lieth not in ſuche corruptible thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. But in this parte we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all diſſolution, exhorting inceſſauntly all men to ſober ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, to the mortification of the fleſh, according to eche mans ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, and to continuall prayer.</p>
                  <p>The laſte point nowe reſteth, whiche is touching outwarde or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and pollicie of the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call eſtate, wherin we thinke (my Lordes) we may ſaye without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that all is at this daye ſo peruerted, ſo confounded, &amp; in ſuch ruyne, as it will be harde for the beſt Maiſters &amp; deuiſers of works that be at this time aliue (wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune order and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te at this preſente of the Churche with the lifes, maners &amp; conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the eccleſiaſtical perſons) to eſpy out the old ſignes, &amp; markes
<pb facs="tcp:19885:27"/> of the buildinge ſo well deuiſed, compaſſed, and framed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, whereof your ſelues can ſomwhat bear witneſſe, hauing theſe dayes paſſed, trauailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the reformation thereof. And becauſe theſe matters be ſo well knowen, we minde not to holde any further purpoſe of them, being ſpecially thinges better to be kept in ſilence, then to be ſpoken of abrode.</p>
                  <p>And to conclude, we proteſte before God and his holie Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, before your Maieſtie and this right honorable companie that ſitteth rounde aboute you, that oure deſire and entent is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to haue the fourme of the Churche brought againe to the naturall purenes and bewtie, in the which it ſo greatly floriſhed in the tyme of the Apoſtles, and of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:27"/>
                  <p>And touching thoſe thinges that ſithen that tyme haue bene added, and haue crepte into the Churche, ſuch of them as ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare clerely to be ſuperſticious, or manifeſtlye contrarie to the worde of God, to be vtterlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed: ſuch as be ſuperfluous, to be cut of: and ſuche as by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience we haue ſene to leade men to ſuperſticion, to be taken qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te awaye. And if anye ſhall be founde expedient, and ſeruinge to edifyinge, beinge iudged to be of that ſorte, after ripe wayinge of them by the auncient Canons and authoritie of the fathers: let them continue, and be reteined, kepte, and obſerued in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of God, according as may be thought to be conuenient for the tyme, place, and perſons, to the intent that drawing all by one ſtring, we may ſerue God in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
<pb facs="tcp:19885:28"/> and trueth, vnder your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and obedience, Sire, and vnder the gouernement of ſuche, as God hathe appoynted, vnder your Maieſtie to haue the order of the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this Realme. And if ther be any, Sire, that yet do thinke that the doctrine wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we make profeſſion, doth by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye meane, diuert, and draw ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes from their obedience, which they ought to beare to their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſuperiours: we haue, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, to anſwere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withal, in good and vpright conſciences.</p>
                  <p>Trueth it is, that we do teache the chieſe and principall obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>once to be due to God, kinge of kinges, and Lord ouer all lordes, For the reſt, if oure writinges be not ſufficient, to purge vs of that foule faute laid vnto oure charge: we will for oure defence, Sire, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage the example of ſo manie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces,
<pb facs="tcp:19885:28"/> Seignories, Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yea and Realmes, refourmed, accordinge vnto this ſelfe ſame doctrine whiche, God be thanked, may ſerue vs for good and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient witneſſes to diſcharge vs. To be ſhorte, we do in this point cleane to S. Paules ſaying, in the 13. Chapiter of his Epiſtle to the Romains, where ſpeaking of the temporall pollicie, he enioyneth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery man expreſſely to be ſubiect to the higher powers. Yea, ſaith Saint Chriſoſtome vpon the ſame place: though thou were an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or Euangeliſte, for ſuch ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction taketh nothing awaye from the ſeruice of God.</p>
                  <p>And in caſe it hath heretofore happened, or may hereafter hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that any cloking them ſelues with oure doctrine, ſhalbe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de culpable of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bellion, to the worſte of youre officers, Sire,
<pb facs="tcp:19885:29"/> we proteſte before God and your Maieſtie, that they be none of ours, and that they can haue no greater enemies to them, ſo doing then we be, ſo farre as oure poore eſtate and condition can reach.</p>
                  <p>To make an end, Sire, oure bounden duetie to do the beſte we can for, the aduauncing of Gods glorie, the obedience and humble ſeruice whiche we owe to your Maieſtie, the zeale and affection that we beare to oure countrey, and ſpecialie to the Churche of God: hath this daye brought vs hyther, truſtynge to Almyghtye God, that folowing the courſe of his goodnes and mercies, he will with his grace work in you, as he did in litle king Ioſias ij. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, two hundred and two yeres<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> auar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſithen. And that vnder your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious gouernement Madame, being aſſiſted with you Sire, and
<pb facs="tcp:19885:29"/> other right honorable Princes, and Lordes of the Councell, the auncient memorie of the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Quene Clotilde, ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued: by whoſe good meane, as Gods inſtrument, the knowledge of his religion, was brought into this Realine. This is our full truſt Sire, for the bringing of whiche thing to paſſe, we are readye to employ oure liues, to the end that ſeruing your Maieſtie in a thinge ſo holy, and ſo commendable, we may ſe and enioye the true golden world, in the which our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt maye be ſerued: to whome be honour and glorie for euer. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Here Maſter de Beze and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie bowed their knees to the gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde: and afterwarde ryſing againe, he preſented a confeſſion to the king, containing the faith of certaine refour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Churches in Fraunce, in ſuche ſort as foloweth.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:30"/>
                  <p>Sire, we beſeche your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie that it maye pleaſe the ſame, to haue no regarde to oure rude and yll polyſhed language, but to waye oure good wylles and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, altogether dedicated to you. And foraſmuche as the poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and articles of our faith and doctrine, bee plainely and at bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lenght conteined in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent confeſſion af oure faith, which we haue once already preſented to your Maieſtie, whereupon the preſent conference is to procede: we humbly beſeche youre Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, to ſhewe vs againe ſo muche fauour, as to receiue it at oure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>andes in this place, truſting by the helpe of the grace of almightie God, that after we ſhall haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred together, in all ſobrietie, and reuerence of his Name, you ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all finde vs all of one accorde. And in caſe oure ſinnes ſhalbe a
<pb facs="tcp:19885:30"/> let, that it ſhall not ſo come to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, yet doubt we not but that your Maieſtie, with his good Councel, ſhalbe hable to bringe the thing to a quiet ende without preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of either partie: as to reaſon and Gods honour ſhal ſeme beſte to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:31"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A briefe writing, exhibited by Maſter Theodore de Beze, to the Quene Mother at Poiſſy, the x. day of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: containing a declaration of certaine pointes proponed by him the day before in the preſence of the King, the Quene Mother, the king of Nauarre, &amp;c. Being preſent alſo there a nomber of Cardinalles and Biſſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, and other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church. 1561.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:32"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Quene.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas your right hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruaunt Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de Beze, hath ſome occaſion to feare that your Maieſtie ſhould not remaine ſatiſfied with a ſpeache that paſſed from him yeſterday, in the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a matter whiche to his great griefe, was by my Lordes the Prelates fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de verye ſtrange. He moſte humble deſireth your Maiſtie, that it maye pleaſe you to vnderſtand at better lenght, ſuche purpoſe as he could not then ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently expreſſe, by reaſon of a noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe reaſed in ſuche ſort, as the knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of his matter was not har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, nor conceiued of the hearers, accordynge as his deſire was it ſhoulde haue bene, and as he ment to haue had it.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:33"/>
                  <p>Madame, the cauſe that ledde me to enter to that matter, was, for that there are manye that for lack of good vnderſtanding of the confeſſion of oure faith, do thinke oure teaching to be to ſhutte out Ieſus Chriſt from his holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, whiche were a manifeſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie. For we do knowe (thankes be geuen to God) that that bleſſed Sacrament was ordeined by the Sonne of God, to the ende that being made more and more parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſubſtaunce of his very bodye and of his very blood, we mought be ſo muche the nere vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and incorporated with him, to drawe to vs thereby the eternall lyfe. And doutleſſe, if it were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it ſhould not be the Sup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>And, Madame, ſo farre be we from willing or meaning to ſay that Chriſte is abſente from his
<pb facs="tcp:19885:33"/> Supper, as contrarily there are no kinde of menne that can leſſe beare ſuch a ſacriledge then we.</p>
                  <p>Trueth it is, that there is a great difference, to ſay that Ieſus Chriſt is preſent at his holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, geuing vnto vs there at his very body and very blood: and to ſay that his body and blood are ioyned with the breade and the wine. I haue confeſſed the firſte, which is the principall. The laſt I haue denied, for that I take it to be directely againſt the veritie of the humaine nature of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Chriſt, and to the article of the Aſcention, as it is conteined in the holie Scripture and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all the auncient Doctours of the Church.</p>
                  <p>I will not here alleage manye places and reaſons. Onely Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame I beſeche your Maieſtie moſte humbly to waye and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:19885:34"/> with your ſelfe, whether of the two opinions carieth with it the more honour to the word and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of God, eyther that, which woulde make vs to beleue that we can not be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the body of Chriſte, vnleſſe it be put and ioyned really with the Sacrament: or els the other that teacheth vs that albeit his body doth preſently remaine in heauen and not elſwhere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet by the ſpirituall vertue of it, and by the meane of a right &amp; true faith, we that be on the earth and do beleue in him, be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his very body and his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blood, as truely and as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye as we ſee with our eyes, and touche with our handes the holye viſible Sacramentes of the bread and wine, whiche he hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that effect.</p>
                  <p>If this declaration. Madame,
<pb facs="tcp:19885:34"/> which long tyme ſithen hath bene ſet forth amonges my wrytynges (albeit I could not yeſterdaye do you to vnderſtande the ſame) may ſatiſfie youre Maieſtie: I ſhall haue greate cauſe to prayſe and thanke God hyghly therefore. If not, I will be ſo bolde as to deſire yet ſo much fauour at your hand, as that I may ſatiſfie your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie more fully by mouth, in the preſence (yf it ſhall ſo be thought nedefull) of ſuch as by whom you ſhall thinke I may receiue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and learnynge, as one that hath great nede thereof, and that doth deſire nothynge ſo muche as to learne more and more, whereby I may be the more hable to do your Maieſtie ſeruice in the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of ſo holſome and ſo holye a concorde and agreement.</p>
                  <p>Theſe be the very wordes by me ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, where with my Lordes the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats ſeme to be much offended.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:35"/>
                  <p>If thereupon they will aſke if<note place="margin">Rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the wordes, ſpoken the daye before.</note> my meaninge be to make Chriſte abſent from his Supper, I ſaye nay: Beleuing neuertheleſſe, that waying the diſtaunce of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes (for ſo muſte we do when the queſtion toucheth corporall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence) and conſidering diſtinctly his humanitie, his bodye is as farre from the breade and wine, as the higheſt parte of heauen is from the earth. If any man will conclude hereof, that we make Chriſte abſent from his Supper, we thinke him to conclude yll.</p>
                  <p>For this honoure do we geue to God, that according to his holye Worde, albeit the body of Chriſte be in heauen, and we on the earth: yet be we made partakers of his body and blood, as verely in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall maner, and by faith, as we do ſee the Sacramentes with our eyes, and put them into our mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes,
<pb facs="tcp:19885:35"/> &amp; do lyue with the ſubſtaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of them, in this corporall lyfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Theſe were my wordes.</p>
                  <q>For the confirmation whereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> here what S. Auguſtine ſayth in his fifte treatie vpon S. Iohn.</q>
                  <p>When Ieſus Chriſt ſayde, you ſhall not alwaye haue me with you, he ſpeake of the preſence of his bodye. For concerninge his Maieſtie, his prouidence, and his inuiſible grace, he hath fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed his promyſe made in an other place: I wil be with you til the ende of the world. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the nature of man taken of him, concerning that he was borne of the virgin Mary, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge that he was crucified, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and rayſed from death to lyfe this ſentence is accompliſhed: you ſhall not alwaye haue me with you. And whye? for that touching his body, he was conuerſaunt 40.
<pb facs="tcp:19885:36"/> dayes with his diſciples, and from the ſame diſciples, folowing him with their eyes, and not going af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, he aſcended into heauen at the ende of 40. dayes, and is no more here.</p>
                  <p>The ſame S Auguſtine in his Epiſtle to Dardanus.</p>
                  <p>In aſmuch as he is God, he is euery where, in that he is man, he is in heauen.</p>
                  <p>Vigilins Byſhoppe of Trent, which wrot againſt the hereſie of the Eutychi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans about the yere of Chriſt 500. ſaieth.</p>
                  <p>The Sonne of God is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from vs touching his humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but touching his diuinitie he ſayeth vnto vs: I am with you till the ende of the worlde. He is with vs, and he is not with vs, for he hath not lefte nor forſaken, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his diuinitie, them that he hath left, and is departed from vs touchinge his humanitie. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge
<pb facs="tcp:19885:36"/> the fourme of a ſeruaunte whiche he hath lift vp into heauen out of our company, he is abſent: but touchinge the fourme of God which departeth not from vs, he is preſent with vs.</p>
                  <p>Againe, when his fleſhe was on the earth, certainly it was not in heauen, now that it is in heauen, as certainely it is not on the earth, and ſo is he abſent as we do ſtyll loke for him, which we do beleue to be with vs on the earth, in that he is the word, to come again from h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auen corporally. and fleſhly.</p>
                  <p>And in an other place, The onely Sonne of God, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was alſo made man, is conceaued in one place by the nature of the fleſh, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in no place touchynge the nature of his diuinitie.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text>
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:37"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19885:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The confeſſion aſweall of the Proteſtants as of there aduerſary par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of lait dayes aſſembled at Poiſſy in Fraunce concerning the preſence of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in the holie Supper whereof let our Papiſtes choſe which beſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them and ſo remoue the errour of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="confessions">
                  <div xml:lang="fre" type="confession">
                     <pb facs="tcp:19885:38"/>
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> La Confeſſion du dernier iour de Septembre, 1561.</head>
                     <p>ENtant que la Foy rend les choſes promiſes preſentes, &amp; que ceſte Foy prent treſueritable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment le corps &amp; le ſang de noſtre ſeigneur Ieſus Chriſt par la vertu du ſainct Eſprit, en ceſtegard nous confeſſons la preſence du corps &amp; du ſang diceluy en la ſaincte Cene: en la quelle il nous preſente, don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; exhibe veritablement la ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance de ſon corps &amp; de ſon ſang par loperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de ſon ſainct Eſprit: &amp; nous receuons, &amp; mangeons ſpirituelement &amp; par foy ceſt corps, qui eſt mort pour nous: pour eſtre os de ſes os, &amp; chair de ſa chair, a fin den eſtre vinifiez, &amp; parceuoir tout ce, qui ſy recoit, a noſtre ſalut.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="eng" type="confession">
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Autre Confeſſion du premier Dottobre, 1561.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19885:38"/>
                     <head type="sub">
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Confeſſion of the one partie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the laſt day of September, 1561.</head>
                     <p>FOr aſmuch as faith maketh preſent the thinges that be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and that the ſam faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth moſt aſſuredly the body and the blood of our lord Ieſus by the vertue of the holie Spirit. In this reſpect we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the preſence of the body &amp; of the blood of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſam our lord Ieſus in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Supper. In the which he preſenteth, geueth &amp; exhibiteth verely the ſubſtance of his body &amp; of his blood by operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his holy Spirit: &amp; we receaue &amp; eat ſpiritually &amp; by faith the body which dead for vs, to be bon of his bones, and fleſh of his fleſh: to the end that we may be quickened and to receaue all that which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit for our ſaluation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="fre" type="confession">
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Confeſſion of the other parte preſented the firſt of October, 1561.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19885:39"/>
                     <p>NOus confeſſons, que Ieſus Chriſt en ſa ſaincte Cene nous preſente, donne, &amp; exhibe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t la ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce de ſon corps &amp; de ſon ſang par loperation de ſon ſainct Eſprit, &amp; que nous receuons &amp; mangeons ſacramentellement, ſpirituellement, &amp; parfoy ce propre corps, qui eſt mort pour nous: pour eſtre os de ſesos, &amp; chair de ſa chair: a fin den eſtre viuifiez, &amp; parcenoir tout ce, qui eſt requis a noſtre ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut. Et pource que la foy appuyee ſur la parolle de Dieu, rend &amp; fait les choſes promiſes preſentes: &amp; que par ceſte foy nous y prenons vraie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; de faict le vray &amp; naturel corps &amp; ſang de noſtre Seigneur par la vertu de ſon ſainct Eſprit: en ceſt egard nous confeſſons la pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence du corps &amp; ſang diceluy en la ſaincte Cene.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="eng" type="confession">
                     <pb facs="tcp:19885:39"/>
                     <p>WE confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt in his holy Supper preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, geueth &amp; verely offereth vnto vs the ſubſtance of his body and his blood, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his holy Spirit. And that we receaue and eat ſacramentally, ſpiritually and by faith that ſam body which died for vs to be bon of his bones and fleſh of his fleſh to the end that we may be quickened and perceaue all that which is requiſet for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And becauſe that faith grounded vpon the word of God maketh and geueth preſent the thinges promiſed: and that by this faith we verely and in effect recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the naturall body and blood of our Lord by the vertue of his holy Spirit, in this reſpecte we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the preſence of his body and blood in the holy Supper.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:19885:40"/>
                     <head>De la part des miniſtres,</head>
                     <list>
                        <head>Maiſtres</head>
                        <item>Pierre Martyr</item>
                        <item>Theodore de Beze</item>
                        <item>Nic. des Gallars</item>
                        <item>Auguſtin Marlorat</item>
                        <item>Iean de Leſpine.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Pourla part des do creurs &amp; eueſques,</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Meſſieurs</head>
                        <item>Leueſque de Vala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</item>
                        <item>Leueſque de Sees</item>
                        <item>Salinac</item>
                        <item>Bouteiller</item>
                        <item>Deſpence.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>For the parte of the miniſters,</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Maſters</head>
                        <item>Peter Martyr</item>
                        <item>Theodore de Beze</item>
                        <item>Nicolas de Gallas</item>
                        <item>Augustin Marlorat</item>
                        <item>Iohn de Leſpine.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>For the part of the doct. &amp; biſchoppes,</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>My lords</head>
                        <item>Biſchop of Valence</item>
                        <item>Biſchoppe of Sees</item>
                        <item>Sallignac</item>
                        <item>Bouceiller</item>
                        <item>Deſpence.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>WE know not whiche of the Confeſſions was preſented by the partie of the Proteſtants neither which by the Biſchoppes but let oure Papiſtes cheſe either and let vs geue glory vnto God
<pb facs="tcp:19885:40"/> whoſe veritie compelleth his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to confeſſe that whiche they haue long denied.</p>
                  </div>
                  <closer>Ariſe, o Lord, let thy enemies be confounded. Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>The end.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>Imprinted at Edinburgh, by Robet Lekprewik,</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio.</p>
                  <p>1561.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
